two things I was thinking about this
week a bit one of
them was um in relation to something you
mentioned or that was mentioned in the
last weeks when we were
talking about
asuba because actually for me that's one
of
the that's one of the contemplations
that I've always found most difficult in
terms of understanding how to how it
should be done
rightly and one of the reasons for that
was because it always kind of came across as
because it always kind of came across as
though it is supposed to be about like
generating a kind of
active almost like hatred or revulsion
towards the body and I couldn't really
get the I didn't understand the point of
that or whether and I was not sure if it was
or whether and I was not sure if it was
really supposed to do
that but then you hear like for example
you were mentioning like last week the
story of the monks who killed themselves
because they practiced
AA
um and
yet I'm not sure if that's really the
point to be like generating almost this
yeah like I said the kind of active
revulsion or disgust what do you mean by
active Okay active is suppos more like I
mean revulsion discuss is the point but
it's on how you do it and on what level
you do it then what I suppose I suppose
I mean like almost an emotional
reaction uh whether it should be that or
is it um
because I mean it reminded me as well of
like something um yeah no I I I know
what you mean I mean yeah uh and uh well
that's I think in initially it will be
emotional you know it will have to be
cuz you uh the the pathway hasn't been
you uh the the pathway hasn't been
trained sufficiently enough but yes the
more correctly it is done less emotional
it is it becomes more
precise in other words it starts to
undermine only the last full
Parts Only the parts that you're
attracted that that you grip with
attract that's undermined by Lust by by
asuba that last is under my b not not
everything else so you you're not
emotionally overwhelmed or disgusted
with everything and nothing and so on so
think about it uh a very specific food
that you really want to
eat and you see no reason to not eat
that I mean there are plenty of other
food but you have no desire towards it
you could eat it it would have the same
end result uh feeding your body but
result uh feeding your body but
particular type of food
and uh you can say no to it of course
each time and and not eat it but you
still remain attracted to
it so then if you were to do a subba or
correctly you would
be finding ways through
contemplation how to undermine that
specific desire toward that specific
food and you wouldn't have to hate all
the food mhm and you wouldn't have to be
emotionally disgusted with
eating all together just this particular
consumption of this particular food you
find disgust you have to find disgust in
it so it's not just convincing yourself
to know e it you actually have to
undermine desire and discuss in regard
to the thing you desire is what
undermines the
desire so there is the active discust
but it's not everywhere and nowhere
which it might be initially yeah which
is why those monks did kill themselves
cuz they got overwhelmed cuz they did
not apply it where it's supposed to
precisely
enough okay that makes sense because so
think about it there is your your
favorite plate with a favorite food on
it and then you find out somebody's
packing it or
Worse would you have desire to eat that
thing on the plate right in front of you
still the same look still the same smell
still the same taste you probably
wouldn't taste someone else's fluids in
it but would you eat it now that you
know that you'll be quite dis and if
somebody to put it in your mouth that
food you would be like spitting it out
disgusted if you were to have to swallow
it you would be disgusted at any part of
involvement with that food that disgust
would be there as a as a the framework
of it cuz now you know what's in it okay
so yeah but that's that's quite a good
it is quite a good example because it's
like that makes sense because the
disgust basically only it's like yes I
would be disgusted in terms of okay yeah
I'm not eating that I don't want to eat
it I don't want to go near it but that's
where it ends basically then you don't
need to kind of go and carry that
discussed with you I don't know like you
know no no if you do means you don't
quite still see the basis where that
last is because then it like if you're
kind of going on about how disgusting it
is it's like there's no need to it's
just okay I just don't need to touch it
I don't need to be involved so the
disgust would be evoked if there is a
careless mental tendency towards eating
it then you get reminded of the disgust
implicit but obviously initially the
whole picture is perverted it's upside
down you start with the desire you start
with the attraction and then disgust has
to be kind of contemplated into to it so
to then become the
normal like uh um natural natural kind
of the first thing you would see if you
were to engage with it would be
discussed as opposed to attraction which
was before the case like oh I want this
and then oh no it's ugly it's disgusting
and then you work and you work but no
this comes up or it's the disgust part
comes
up and so then that's like because in
terms of then how like how I relate to
the body for example in general okay if
I need to go to the toilet I need to go
to the toilet if I need to wash it it
needs to be washed I need to kind of
engage with it to a certain
extent but then so when would then if
you were to contemplate discust rightly
when would that when would then discust
arise in regard to your own
body for seeing it like if seeing it as
a I don't know an object of attraction
seual sexual attraction for example
sexual attraction okay or in terms of um
I don't know like if somebody wants to
decorate it or yeah yeah if you were to
take it as a as a thing of beauty to be
displayed externally for others or
something uh if you were to uh use it as
a basis for pleasure in general yeah
that discussed can undermine that as
well but if the Mind stops going in
those directions
there is no discuss to be certainly to
be there actively
felt and you that's what I mean like you
can engage with this without in in in
those kind of neutral ways without I
mean the ways that are not sexual not uh
vain not about beautification not about
gaining pleasure through the
body uh admiring being admired on the
account of physical that that's also
again that would be undermined by the
discussed by a
subba or even like non not necessarily
like I want to be admired by others as a
kind of
a as a human being in terms
of being seen in a certain way by I
think even that would be kind of under
mind no by because it's all kind of on
the basis of this well bag of gones yeah
I mean yeah sure you yeah
and I guess the other thing that at
least in the past was not
really clear is like what clear for me
was how
to because it's often spoke about in in
terms of like how to practically go
about doing it let's say like how do you
how how do you contemplate a subba
and especially when it comes to like
then I there list of like internal
organs and stuff I don't know to me my I
think of an internal organ and my mind
just is like that's just something I'm
imag I think for most people that's what
it is because that's why like when you
look at these uh Suba contemplations
done as me methods and techniques they
just become this kind of empty recital
of this visualized sort of abstract
ideas that then people kind of
implicitly hope will somehow cause
passion to disappear from me um and uh
and even like just just looking at the
asuba pictures and uh contemplating like
you know in the suas contemplate the
bodies on the channel ground and stuff
you realize even that you might get that
initial shock but then you get used to
it you overcome it and you stop seeing
it and then the lust is back and then
now you just you just numb to to these
these shocking contemplations and sights
and sounds and smells and so on because
if you're just a a finding it kind of as
a as a as a
blanket um uh practice that you then but you
um uh practice that you then but you
don't see the relationship between that
and the actual lust and attraction when
it is present it's not going to work CU
cuz you you're not making the the
necessary connection between the two um
so practically you want to you want to
contemplate a subba as I said
first well in order to make the
connection so that that subba can be
applied rightly on the things that can
be undermined by it you need to stop
just habitually trying to get rid of
those things when they arise so if you
do have a desire for a food on the plate
yes you can't just start eating it so
you have to
restrain um that also means you need to stop
um that also means you need to stop
looking at it smelling it holding it
bringing it close to your face and so on
whatever you would but I'm not eating it
yeah but but you're doing everything
else around it so you need to withdraw
your senses from it and then the mental
pressure on account of that desire
that's what you can't you have to endure
now rightly without going back to these
objects so if that endurance is done
sufficiently um then you get to recognize okay so
um then you get to recognize okay so
it's this desire even I'm I'm away from
the the plate of food that's still on my
mind mentally it's still there that's
what what I need to so I do want it so
how do I make myself not
wanted but that can be only done
correctly if you are first withdrawn
from it with your senses because if you
are not doesn't matter what you're
contemplating your senses still keep you
connected to it in that wrong way
through the desire so if somebody is
withdrawn and it's not going back to it
beside sound smell taste touches to the
the most desirous thing then recognizes
that he wants it okay how do I undermine
the want well by taking the same images
of this desirous thing and
basically contemplating into
them a non Desiring aspect which is
there of the same thing not something
else within that same thing you wanted
you have to find the aspects of the same
thing that are not wanted so at the same
time you do have this desire that you
are then actively undermining through
the contemplation of that same thing
aspects of the same thing that are
factually not
desirable so if there is an attraction
to a body through the pleasure you can
get through the body you can't just get
rid of this I'll replace it with a
discust and just just look at this and
get this shock effect and then I'll stop
thinking about it that won't work it
will work initially novelty will run off
and you're back to where you started
plus now you think a subba doesn't work
um so you when you recognize that desire
if it's endured and you're not trying to
get rid of it
you do find factual disgusting aspects
of the same body and leave them there
with the desire don't try to force the
desire out with by by by by pushing it
out with these other now contemplated
aspects just leave the disgust however
faint it might be leave it there with
the desire it will neutralize
desire it will neutralize
it and that's the point that's like
finding the balance tuning it rightly
cuz again if you you do recognize the
the the disgusting parts and now you
want to force them even quicker to get
rid of the desire but you'll be doing
that through the desire so you kind of
fail from the Middle Ground from the
middle way uh and that's it and now you realize
way uh and that's it and now you realize
in in the broad terms Whenever there is
attraction to the
body at the same time there will be a uh
um an aspect that is factually
nonattractive simultaneous with it and
that's what you get to see and then all
you need to do is attend to the aspect
that's that's that's nonattractive and
refuse to attend to the aspect that's
attractive both are in your mind
simultaneously present but you do not
attend to those that are agreeable you
attend to the factually disagreeable and
that's it and if there is an Impulse to
do it harder to do more of it to do it
quicker well you also refrain from the
impulse just attend it rightly and leave
it there it will do its work
cuz that's the thing like I would say I
mean it's kind of a Common Thread with
nearly all of
the the hindrances but like say this the
the the aspects that are
nondesirable are not something that
require your input to keep feeding them they're
your input to keep feeding them they're
just there on their own whereas and it's
the exact opposite with the well they
need to be discerned discerned from the
thing and that's what mean like you have
to start enduring that thing that desire
on the mental level first because that's
where you're going to find these uh
non-attractive aspects of it if you
refusing to endure it and then seeking
the non-attractive aspects they're all
going to be rooted in aversion towards
this I just want to get rid of this
thing and it's not going to
work but if it's endured
correctly without as I said blindly
aversive trying to just get rid of this
eye cuz it's painful no bear the pain
and then the the the the aspects that
are factually not attractive you know
you're supposed to look for them now you
can look in that very desire while
desire is pressure in you that's fine
all I need to do is not go back to sight
sound smell taste States associated with
it this pressure can go forever as far
as I'm concerned it can't make me act
unless I choose to yes it's unpleasant
while that's there you start to look at
the factually discusting aspects of the
same very
thing Discerning them CU they are
there so while you're pressure to
consume that plate you're Discerning
that somebody is constantly spitting in
it and then have but there is still
desire to eat it you still feel that
hunger but you remain attending to the
knowledge that somebody's Pat in it that
that it's that it's contaminated that it
is so
and you will lose desire towards it not
overnight but you don't have to worry
about
it that's what I meant like it's not
um like it's something you have to
notice basically these these non-desired
aspects not something that you have to
necessarily I think be like well if
you're kind of creating trying to create
it and fabricate it that's going to be
that I think is that kind of what you
meant by do if you try to fabricate it
uh coming out of the aversion towards
the the the pressure of Desire it's not
going to work and there is you those
aspects everybody knows them usually you
find them after you try to satisfy your
desires then you're disgusted cuz you
overate so people experience this cast
in regard to the same things they're
attracted to they just don't know how to
experience it at the same time
so we're back onto that practice of
simultaneity again you get the desire
you're not trying to get rid of it you
just try to bring out a broader context
of this cast while desire is pressuring
you and leave it there leave that
balance there
last cuz many people would have
experienced something they really want
and then get it and then oh well that
was it or or even worse they they they go
it or or even worse they they they go
through great lens to to obtain what
they want to consume what they want to
to to sight sound smell taste touches
and then they burn out through all that
effort and then they have it and then
they discust it with it discust it with
themselves they just feel like oh this
is
depressing but they feel it after so
next time the desire comes they're going
to seek it again because they won't be
making the effort to bring up the
factual discusting aspects of their
thing that they have experienced after
desire would have subsided and bring
together at the same time while the
pressure is there no because pressure
being uncomfortable will kind of make
them lose perspective uh out of a verion
to try to get rid of that discomfort and
pain and that's that practice in the
suit do describe he doesn't grasp the
sides and the features that would be
incitive of lost and takeing in that
direction yeah so you do have the desire
you do have the pressure you're having
images in your mind and that's where
you're making that choice am I allowing
and grasping signs and features that are
associated with desire and attractive
aspects or do I refuse to basically um
allow my mind to to dwell on those and
proliferate but instead I feed the
context of the discuss in regard to the
same desire that still felt that I'm not
just trying to get rid and replace with
with a r through a random practice of
meditation method or technique
and that's why the organs and so on
because if they are seen on that level
like as a
simultaneous thing phenomena present
there with the desire towards the thing
that's comprised of those organs then it
will be it will be very efficient it
won't be just a like yes kidney liver
lungs as people just recite magically
like a magical Mantra no it will be oh a
bag of skin so doesn't matter how
specific your desire might have been how
strong this completely kind of just
deflates it if sustained long
enough and also um those organs listed
they are pretty much Universal to
anything any anybody yours or others any
desire involved in between the two so it
doesn't matter the occasion doesn't
matter the specific scenario liver
kidney brain bile urine P skin hair it's
there has to be there as a necessary
basis so but I desire it yes there is a
desire towards the specific form that
those things have taken Now bring up the
aspects of those things that are there
bring up the aspects of of of yeah just
imagine holding a kidney or a or a
bloody lung in your hand it's like oh
okay put it simultaneously there don't
try to replace one with the other and
leave that setup there
so then the disgust will work to the
extent that it needs to work you know
it's like trying to neutralize acid with
alkaline alkaline will neutral only it
will neutralize only acid Parts you acid
drops you pour the alkaline it will only
react with the parts of that are acid
you're not going to react with other
things you're not going to destroy
everything else and then you can just wash
else and then you can just wash
everything away
reminds me of there's this
um one of the verses I really like in
the terata from the nuns
where um so it's like the nun is walking
in the forest or something and some guy
comes and is like I don't know harassing
her and so on and uh say oh come with me
come and marry me and you'll be dressed
and find clothes and everything and
leave this House's life uh and she asks
him U what what do you what do you find
so attractive in this in this body in
this spones and he oh your eyes your
eyes are like a
dough so beautiful and so oh really okay
my eyes you want and then she
take takes out the eye and so here you
go and so and he was shocked and
disgusted and he was shocked and
disgusted and like so it's same of like
you were saying it's the same thing but
like in and of itself yeah nobody wants
it
yeah yeah exactly like it's the form and
the shape where the attraction
rests in and of itself that which makes
that shape and form it's like
oh but that's not seen at the same time
and also like a person doesn't need to
go and actively seek out the attraction
to practice a subba in regard to it
because if you have not well if you're
not free from passion means even without
any specific things coming up your mind
coming up like um uh uh sort of like
desire taking over your mind even
without any specific uh sight sound
smell taste tou or image you are within
that domain so in other words you do
carry that basis for attraction with you
you don't go around and when you see the
body when the body pops up do you first
see the disgusting aspect naturally or
do you first see the attractive aspect
naturally well if it's not the the
former means you do carry your last with
you so then you could start practicing
this asuba anytime on that right level like
asuba anytime on that right level like
it does not require a specific arousal
or desire or this to counter
it like fundamentally you go around
carrying a view that bodies are not
disgusting that's that's the first thing
you see then you try to see the asuba
and so on but for as long as that order
is not changed up whereby the views that
the bodies are
disgusting um as in like not just the
intellectual idea but when bodies are
experienced in the way that could be uh
provocative of Desire well it's
provocative of discust not desire same
like you would not be disgusted with a
thing that's on the plate that you don't
deem edible but if somebody offers you to eat
edible but if somebody offers you to eat
it then you're like whoa no now now it's
now it's genuinely disgusting because
you brought up that context